1. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding an examination under oath (EUO)?
A. An EUO must be completed in a single sitting.
B. The demand letter should include a definite time and place for the examination, as well as the documents the examinee must bring.
C. An insured can submit written responses to the questions given by the insurer.
D. The insured can invoke the Fifth Amendment right against self-incrimination and refuse to answer any question in the EUO.

B is correct (Module 2 – Obj 6).
 

A is incorrect. If the EUO is not completed in one sitting, a continuance can be scheduled.
C is incorrect. An insured required to give an EUO must appear in person and give oral testimony.
D is incorrect. The person being examined must answer any question material to the loss and, for such a question, cannot invoke the Fifth Amendment right against self-incrimination.

2. An item’s original cost is usually irrelevant for claim-settling purposes. However, original cost is sometimes used to settle losses on:
A. Commercial buildings.
B. Inventory.
C. Fine art.
D. Tenant’s improvements.

D is correct (Module 6 – Obj 2).
 

A is incorrect. Commercial buildings are often covered using actual cash value.
B is incorrect. Inventory is sometimes covered for the selling price.
C is incorrect. Stated or Agreed Value is often the approach used for fine art.

3. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding the salvor’s role in the merchandise loss settlement process?
A. The salvor takes title to the merchandise prior to the sale.
B. A salvor knows the best people to contact if a sale is held and can ensure that the best possible price is obtained.
C. The insured is directly liable for the salvor’s fees.
D. If the salvor thinks the merchandise is safe on the insured’s premises, the insured bears the risk if the salvor is incorrect.

B is correct (Module 7 – Obj 4).
 

A is incorrect. The insured retains title to the merchandise.
C is incorrect. The salvor’s fees are paid out of the merchandise sale proceeds.
D is incorrect. If the salvor thinks the merchandise is safe on the insured’s premises, the insurer bears the risk if the salvor is incorrect.

4. Which one of the following would be considered revenue for a manufacturing business?
A. Income received from an insurance claim.
B. Income from sale of investments.
C. Income from sale of real estate.
D. Income from operations.

D is correct (Module 8 – Obj 3).
 

For a manufacturing business, only money generated from a business’s operations is considered revenue. Operations do not include the purchase or sale of major assets, such as real estate.

5. In which of the following situations is an insurance company most likely to exercise the “repair or replace” option of a property insurance policy?
A. The damaged property has a very small markup at the retail level.
B. The loss is relatively infrequent for the insurer.
C. The insured is suspected of trying to profit from the claim.
D. The insured property is readily available in a department store.

C is correct (Module 6 – Obj 2).
 

Insurers exercise the “repair or replace” option under the following circumstances:

The insured is suspected of trying to profit from the claim.
Using the “repair or replace” option is less expensive than the cash option.


6. Which one of the following represents a method commonly used by adjusters and accountants to determine the value owed under a Business Income Coverage (BIC) form?
A. Gross profit plus continuing expenses.
B. Net income less continuing expenses.
C. Gross profit less noncontinuing expenses.
D. Net income plus noncontinuing expenses.

C is correct (Module 8 – Obj 4).
 

The two common methods used by adjusters and accountants to determine the value owed under a Business Income Coverage (BIC) form are:
• Net income plus continuing expense method.
• Gross profit less noncontinuing expense method.

7. Fire investigation reports should accomplish all of the following, EXCEPT:
A. Reconstruct the loss scene.
B. Document the damage patterns.
C. Show mechanisms of ignition clearly.
D. Indicate all parties with an insurable interest.

D is correct (Module 4 – Obj 1).
 

Fire investigation reports should have the following elements:

Document the damage patterns.
Reconstruct the loss scene.
Show mechanisms of ignition clearly.
Eliminate all other sources of ignition.
8. Which one of the following is an indicator of fraud associated with the claims process?
A. Insured can recall place and date of purchase for items of significant value.
B. Insured has receipts for expensive items but not inexpensive items.
C. Insured indicates no distress over prospect of an examination under oath.
D. Insured provides receipts from same supplier that are numbered in sequence.

D is correct (Module 5 – Obj 5).
 

A is incorrect. An insured not being able to recall the place and date of purchase for items of significant value is an indicator associated with the claim process.
B is incorrect. An insured providing numerous receipts for inexpensive items, but no receipts for items of significant value, is an indicator associated with the claim process.
C is incorrect. An insured indicating distress over prospect of an examination under oath is an indicator associated with the claim process.

9. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding cold smoke?
A. It can deeply stain masonry.
B. It is found closer to the source of the fire than hot smoke.
C. It can often be removed by vacuuming and washing the affected area.
D. It typically leaves a pungent odor.

C is correct (Module 4 – Obj 1).
 

A is incorrect. Hot smoke can deeply stain masonry.
B is incorrect. Hot smoke is found closer to the source of the fire than cold smoke.
D is incorrect. Cold smoke typically does not leave a pungent odor.

10. When real property is owned by two joint tenants, and one of the tenants dies, the surviving tenant will:
A. Not have any ownership interest in the property.
B. Have unrestricted ownership and control of the entire property.
C. Own a fractional share of the property.
D. Have full use and possession of the property only for the remainder of his or her life.

B is correct (Module 2 – Obj 3).
 

A is incorrect. When property is owned as joint tenancy and one of the tenants dies, the surviving tenants receive the decedent’s share.
C is incorrect. With a tenancy in common interest, the surviving tenant will not be entitled to the decedent’s share and will therefore only own their own fractional share of the property that was owned prior to the other tenant’s death.
D is incorrect. A life tenant would have full use and possession of the property for the remainder of his or her life.

11. The voluntary and intentional relinquishment of a known contractual right by an insurer is known as:
A. Estoppel.
B. Rejection.
C. Compromise.
D. Waiver.

D is correct (Module 2 – Obj 5).
 

A waiver is the intentional relinquishment of a known contractual right.

12. Certain professionals specialize in the cleaning of equipment, merchandise, inventory, structures, and personal property after a loss caused by fire, smoke, or another peril. These professionals are commonly referred to as:
A. Salvors.
B. Origin and cause experts.
C. Private investigators.
D. Restoration specialists.

D is correct (Module 1 – Obj 4).
 

A is incorrect. Salvors don’t clean merchandise; they typically are hired to separate damaged and undamaged merchandise.
B is incorrect. Origin and cause experts determine how and where a fire began.
C is incorrect. Private investigators are typically employed when insurance fraud is suspected.

13. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding water damage losses?
A. The key to successful adjustment is quickly stopping the water from flowing so the drying process can begin.
B. Finding a leak within walls and ceilings is fairly easy because water typically travels in a straight line.
C. If a hurricane has torn a hole in a roof and rain is entering the structure, finding the source of the water damage is still somewhat difficult.
D. The BPP and HO-3 policies do not provide any coverage for the cost of tearing out and replacing part of a building damaged by water.

A is correct (Module 4 – Obj 2).
 

B is incorrect. Finding a leak within walls and ceilings can be difficult because water doesn’t necessarily travel in a straight line.
C is incorrect. If a hurricane has torn a hole in a roof and rain is entering the structure, finding the source of the water damage is easy.
D is incorrect. The BPP and HO-3 policies provide coverage for the cost of tearing out and replacing part of a building when necessary to repair a leaking system.

14. Which one of the following is a sign of a fire that has been intentionally set?
A. Fire started at the corner of the building.
B. All the windows in the building are open.
C. A single point of origin.
D. Fire started inside an electrical appliance.

B is correct (Module 5 – Obj 3).
 

Unusual ventilation, such as all windows open, is a sign that a fire was intentionally set.

 

A is incorrect. A fire starting at the corner of a building is not a sign of an intentionally set fire.
C is incorrect. Multiple points of origin is evidence of an intentionally set fire.
D is incorrect. It’s typical for an accidental fire to begin inside an electrical appliance.

15. Which one of the following does the insurer need to prove to deny an arson claim?
A. The fire occurred within one week of the policy beginning date.
B. The insured had a motive for starting the fire.
C. The fire was started by or at the direction of the insured.
D. The fire started in one location in the building.

C is correct (Module 5 – Obj 3).
 

A is incorrect. The insured can deny a claim if they can prove the fire was started at the direction of the insured. However, the arson defense can be asserted regardless of when the fire began.
B is incorrect. Proving the insured’s motive is helpful but not required to deny an arson claim.
D is incorrect. Denying an arson claim is based on proving who started the fire rather than where and how it started.

16. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding the right of subrogation?
A. The insurer has the right to receive only the amount it has paid in a claim.
B. Some policies permit the insured to waive rights of recovery after a loss.
C. It is the most common approach used to resolve insurer disagreements regarding overlapping coverage.
D. The insurer’s decision not to pursue subrogation precludes the insured from pursuing a negligent third party.

A is correct (Module 1 – Obj 5).
 

B is incorrect. Some policies permit the insured to waive rights of recovery BEFORE a loss.
C is incorrect. Compromise is the most common approach used to resolve insurer disagreements regarding overlapping coverage.
D is incorrect. The insurer’s decision not to pursue subrogation does NOT preclude the insured from pursuing a negligent third party.

17. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding the peril of lightning?
A. Lightning damages more sturdy parts before it damages the more fragile components.
B. Lightning typically causes damage to pipes and rotors.
C. If the picture tube of a TV is the only component damaged, it is unlikely a result of lightning.
D. If only the heating coils are damaged in an electric dryer, it was probably a result of lightning.

C is correct (Module 4 – Obj 1).
 

A is incorrect. Lightning damages more fragile parts before it damages the sturdier components.
B is incorrect. Lightning does not damage parts such as rotors and pipes.
D is incorrect. Lightning damages more fragile parts before it damages the sturdier components. Heating coils are sturdier than parts like the dryer’s timer. Therefore, if only the heating coils are damaged, it was probably not caused by lightning.

18. In order to begin a theft claim investigation, an adjuster first:
A. Confirms who owns the property.
B. Determines if theft is a covered peril under the policy.
C. Evaluates who has an insurable interest in the property.
D. Ascertains if a police report has been filed.

B is correct (Module 4 – Obj 4).
 

While all of the steps listed are important in adjusting theft claims, the first step for the adjuster is to determine if theft is a covered peril under the policy.

19. Which one of the following professionals plays a specific role in an arson investigation by preserving chemical residue from a fire scene?
A. Professional investigator.
B. Fire marshal.
C. Origin and cause expert.
D. Forensic chemist.

D is correct (Module 5 – Obj 4).
 

Forensic chemists detect, identify, and preserve chemical residues from fire scenes that are relevant to determining the cause of a fire. A forensic chemist must be trained in preserving evidence in a legally admissible manner.

20. The first step in remediating any mold damage is to:
A. Sanitize moldy surfaces using strong cleansers.
B. Conduct an air sampling analysis.
C. Immediately dry any moisture and correct the source of water infiltration.
D. Tear out the affected area and replace it with like-kind materials.

C is correct (Module 4 – Obj 3).
 

The New York City Guidelines have been used by some states as a standard for remediating mold. Under this document, the first step in remediating any mold damage is to immediately dry any moisture and correct the source of water infiltration.

21. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding adjusting standards relating to a catastrophe?
A. Adjusters should always waive the sworn proof of loss in a catastrophe situation.
B. Adjusters seldom have to reopen files from a catastrophe because most losses are total losses.
C. Adjusters should attempt to pay any amount to close a claim rapidly, because the prices of goods and services are likely to increase after a catastrophe.
D. Adjusters are likely to be less thorough in their adjusting procedures and more flexible about settlement costs.

D is correct (Module 4 – Obj 6).
 

A is incorrect. An adjuster may very well waive the sworn proof of loss requirement for some insured after a catastrophe, but this should not happen in all situations.
B is incorrect. Adjusters may have to reopen many files from a catastrophe. Many settlements are made at actual cash value, and the claim is then concluded later with a replacement cost settlement.
C is incorrect. A big mistake that adjusters make after a catastrophe is to pay any amount to settle the claim. Adjusters should evaluate losses and pay an appropriate amount that indemnifies (and not enriches) the insureds.

22. Which one of the following represents a difference between a nonwaiver agreement and a reservation of rights letter?
A. A nonwaiver agreement is signed by the insured, while the reservation of rights letter is not.
B. A nonwaiver agreement is drafted by the insurer, while a reservation of rights letter is drafted by the insured.
C. A nonwaiver agreement is delivered to the insured by certified mail, while a reservation of rights letter is only kept in the insurer’s file and is not sent to the insured.
D. A nonwaiver agreement is only effective in avoiding wavier, while a reservation of rights letter is only effective in avoiding estoppel.

A is correct (Module 3 – Obj 2).
 

A nonwaiver agreement should be signed by the insured. A reservation of rights letter is not signed by the insured, but evidence of the insured’s receipt of the letter should be obtained.

 

B is incorrect. Both a nonwaiver agreement and a reservation of rights letter are drafted by the insurer.
C is incorrect. A reservation of rights letter should be delivered to the insured by certified mail with return receipt requested.
D is incorrect. Both a nonwaiver agreement and a reservation of rights letter can help an insurer avoid waiver and estoppel.

23. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding the role of the umpire in an appraisal?
A. The umpire is chosen by the two appraisers to resolve disputes regarding the amount of the loss.
B. The umpire is chosen by the two appraisers to resolve coverage disputes.
C. The umpire is chosen by the insurer to resolve disputes regarding the amount of the loss.
D. The umpire is chosen by the insured to resolve coverage disputes.

A is correct (Module 6 – Obj 6).
 

If the two appraisers (one for the insurer and one for the insured) disagree about the amount of the loss, the two appraisers choose an umpire to resolve this dispute. Appraisals do not resolve coverage disputes.

24. Which one of the following conditions would cause coverage of a Builders Risk form to end?
A. 30 days have passed since the project was completed.
B. The insured no longer has any interest in the property.
C. A lessee signed a lease for one office in the building and moved into that office today.
D. Construction has been halted due to a strike, but the property owner intends to complete the building after the strike ends.

B is correct (Module 9 – Obj 5).
 

The following are conditions that could cause coverage of a Builders Risk form to end:

The policy is cancelled, or 90 (not 30) days have passed since the project was completed.
The insured no longer has any interest in the property.
The construction is abandoned, and the insured has no intent to complete the project.
The owner or purchaser accepts the property.
60 days have passed after the building has been wholly or partially occupied or leased.


25. In the case of a property insurance policy insuring a building, the value of the underlying land is:
A. Irrelevant.
B. The amount a willing buyer would pay a willing seller.
C. The appraised value based on property tax records.
D. A percentage of the value of the building.

A is correct (Module 6 – Obj 1).
 

The value of real property overall includes both the land’s value and the structure’s value. However, for property insurance purposes, only the structure is insured, making the value of the land irrelevant.

26. Reasons for deductibles include:
A. They require the insured to share in the loss.
B. They eliminate the insurer’s obligation for small losses.
C. They lower the policy premiums.
D. All of the above.

D is correct (Module 6 – Obj 3).
 

Reasons for deductibles include:

Require insured to share in the loss.
Eliminate insurer’s obligation for small losses.
Lowers premiums for insured.
27. If a homeowner decides to permanently move following damage to a residence premises, the Additional Living Expense coverage from Coverage D - Loss of use applies for:
A. The shortest amount of time required to reasonably settle elsewhere.
B. The remaining time until the end of the policy period.
C. The shortest amount of time required to repair the original premises.
D. 60 days after the loss.

A is correct (Module 8 – Obj 6).
 

If the homeowner decides to permanently relocate, payment will be for the shortest time required for the household to settle elsewhere.

28. Which one of the following represents the best way for a large contractor that has many pieces of equipment which might be owned, rented, or borrowed to insure their equipment?
A. Scheduled coverage.
B. Single limit coverage.
C. Specified perils coverage.
D. Blanket limit coverage.

D is correct (Module 9 – Obj 4).
 

A blanket limit allows a contractor to insure all the tools and equipment they use, whether they are owned, borrowed, or rented.

29. Which one of the following represents an individual or institution that lends money to a person so they can purchase a home?
A. Bailor.
B. Mortgagee.
C. Trustee.
D. Lienholder.

D is correct (Module 2 – Obj 4).
 

A is incorrect. A bailor is the owner of the personal property in bailment.
B is incorrect. A mortgagee is the borrow in a mortgage, not the lender.
C is incorrect. A trustee is someone who has the legal title to a property but is responsible that it be used, handled, and transferred solely for the benefit of the beneficiary.

30. If an insurer’s ability to fully investigate a claim is hindered by the insured’s late notice of the loss, it is said that the insurer’s rights have been:
A. Negated.
B. Estopped.
C. Prejudiced.
D. Pre-empted.

C is correct (Module 3 – Obj 3).
 
Prejudiced (due to late notice) is when an insured’s ability to investigate, settle, or defend a claim is adversely affected by an insured’s late notice of loss.

31. The method of determining amounts payable for a property loss by subtracting depreciation from replacement cost is:
A. Actual Cash Value.
B. Functional Valuation Approach.
C. Market Value.
D. Obsolescence.

A is correct (Module 6 – Obj 1).
 

B is incorrect. Function Valuation Approach is a valuation method in which the insurer is required to pay no more than the cost to repair or replace the damaged or destroyed property with property that is its function equivalent.
C is incorrect. Market Value is the price at which a particular piece of property could be sold on the open market by an unrelated buyer and seller.
D is incorrect. Obsolescence is the loss of value caused by changes in technology or fashion.

32. All of the following must be considered when determining if an item of property is a fixture, EXCEPT:
A. Attachment.
B. Adaptation.
C. Intent.
D. Relative cost.

D is correct (Module 2 – Obj 2).
 

The three important considerations in distinguishing between personal property and a fixture are attachment, adaptation, and intent.

33. Which one of the following represents the best description of an income statement?
A. A list of assets and liabilities.
B. A report of shareholders’ equity.
C. A statement of net worth.
D. A report of profits or losses.

D is correct (Module 7 – Obj 3).
 

An income statement is the financial statement that reports an organization's profit or loss for a specific period by comparing the revenues generated with the expenses incurred to produce those revenues.

34. In which one of the following situations is a general nonwaiver used?
A. The insurer is concerned that the claims investigation will take longer than the law allows.
B. The insurer commits estoppel.
C. The insurer is concerned about investigating a claim before the insured has substantially complied with the policy’s duties after loss conditions.
D. The insurer becomes aware of a specific coverage problem or defense based on information received during an inspection of the damaged property.

C is correct (Module 3 – Obj 2).
 

A general nonwaiver agreement is commonly used in daily claims adjusting whenever the insurer is concerned about investigating a claim before the insured has substantially complied with the policy’s duties after loss conditions. A specific nonwaiver is used whenever the insurer becomes aware of a specific coverage problem or defense.

35. If a claims representative involves a salvor in a claim:
A. The insured is responsible for the salvor’s fees.
B. The salvor arranges a sale if the merchandise is salable.
C. The salvor takes ownership of the damaged goods.
D. The salvor takes over the claims handling process.

B is correct (Module 7 – Obj 4).
 

A is incorrect. The salvor’s fees are paid for by the insurer.
C is incorrect. The salvor can help sell the salvaged goods, but the ownership does not pass to the salvor.
D is incorrect. The claims representative maintains control of the claims handling process.

36. Various incidental expenses that may result from physical loss or from a delay in completion of a construction project are known as:
A. Constructive costs.
B. Continuing costs.
C. Extra costs.
D. Soft costs.

D is correct (Module 9 – Obj 5).
 

Soft costs are those such as interest, real estate tax, advertising, architects and engineers fees, and legal and accounting fees that may result from physical loss or from a delay in completion of a construction project.

37. When making decisions about coverage for a claim, the claims representative needs to do all of the following, EXCEPT:
A. Keep an open mind about different interpretations of the policy.
B. Memorize policy language.
C. Avoid letting emotions and preconceived notions get in the way.
D. Gather all the relevant facts.

B is correct (Module 3 – Obj 1).
 

It is unreasonable to expect a claims representative to memorize every word of every policy.

38. Which one of the following items would be included on an income statement?
A. Depreciation.
B. Inventory.
C. Accounts Payable.
D. Owners’ Equity.

A is correct (Module 8 – Obj 2).
 

Depreciation is included on an income statement but not on a balance sheet.

 

B is incorrect. Inventory is listed as an asset on the balance sheet.
C is incorrect. Accounts payable is listed as a liability on the balance sheet.
D is incorrect. Owners equity (also known as Shareholders Equity) is listed on the balance sheet.

39. Which one of the following professionals plays a specific role in an arson investigation by examining an insured’s financial records to identify trends in the insured’s business?
A. Special investigation unit.
B. Attorney.
C. Origin and cause expert.
D. Forensic accountant.

D is correct (Module 5 – Obj 4).
 

A common motive for arson is financial. Involving a forensic accountant in an investigation can help the claims rep discover a significant amount regarding the insured’s financial condition.

40. The first step after a claims representative is assigned a claim should be to:
A. Identify the policy.
B. Contact the insured.
C. Determine cause of loss.
D. Investigate the claim.

A is correct (Module 1 – Obj 1).
 

After receiving a claim assignment, the first thing a claims representative should do is to identify the policy in force on the date of the loss and review the policy.

41. Under Coverage D - Loss of Use, which one of the following scenarios is most likely to be covered by Additional Living Expense coverage?
A. A lightning strike causes an electrical short in a home office, destroying the computer and home entertainment system.
B. A fire in the oven spreads and causes severe damage to the kitchen.
C. Rising flood waters from heavy rain severely damage the bedrooms and bathrooms.
D. Water from a flooded river seeps into the basement and results in two feet of standing water.

B is correct (Module 8 – Obj 6).
 

A is incorrect. Damage to a homeowner’s computer and home entertainment system would not cause a residence premises to be considered “unfit to live in.”
C is incorrect. ISO homeowners forms do not cover flood damage, so loss of use resulting from flooding would not be covered under Coverage D.
D is incorrect. ISO homeowners forms do not cover flood damage, so loss of use resulting from flooding would not be covered under Coverage D.

42. The party that has possession of personal property but no legal ownership of the property is a(n):
A. Agent.
B. Bailor.
C. Bailee.
D. Trustee.

C is correct (Module 2 – Obj 3).
 

The bailee is the party temporarily possessing the personal property in a bailment.

 

A is incorrect. The agent is the party in an agency relationship that is authorized by the principal to act on the principle’s behalf.
B is incorrect. The bailor is the owner of the personal property in bailment.
D is incorrect. The trustee is someone who has the legal title to a property but is responsible that it be used, handled, and transferred solely for the benefit of the beneficiary.

43. Property Claims Services (PCS) of Verisk defines a catastrophe as an event that causes:
A. $15,000,000 or more in direct insured property losses and affects over 1,000 insureds.
B. $20,000,000 or more in direct insured property losses and affects over 1,000 insureds.
C. $25,000,000 or more in direct insured property losses and affects a significant number of insureds.
D. $30,000,000 or more in direct insured property losses and affects a significant number of insureds.

C is correct (Module 4 – Obj 5).
 

Property Claims Services (PCS) of Verisk defines a catastrophe as an event that causes $25,000,000 or more in direct insured property losses and affects a significant number of insureds and insurers.

44. During an initial meeting with an insured at a loss site, a claims representative should:
A. Provide an estimate of the amount to be covered under the policy.
B. Explain any possible policy violations, exclusions, or limitations.
C. Approve or deny the claim.
D. Conduct an examination under oath of the insured.

B is correct (Module 1 – Obj 1).
 

During an initial meeting a claims representative should explain any possible policy violations, exclusions or limitations that could affect coverage because withholding that information can be considered a breach of the claims representative’s duties.

45. Which one of the following should a claims representative be aware of when taking a statement from an insured?
A. If an attorney isn’t present, the insured is likely to make false statements.
B. The statement could waive the insurer’s right to obtain an examination under oath.
C. The statement needs to be transcribed and signed by the insured.
D. All facts presented in the statement should be corroborated by two witnesses.

B is correct (Module 3 – Obj 2).
 

In some jurisdictions, a claims investigation in which the claims representative obtains a detailed statement from the insured covering the facts and extent of the loss waives the proof of loss and examination under oath conditions.

46. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding a proof of loss?
A. The insurer can reject the proof of loss without giving a reason for the rejection.
B. The insurer can reject the proof of loss and at any point during the claims process.
C. The insurer can waive the necessity for a proof of loss if it makes the adjusting process more efficient.
D. The insured can decline to provide a requested proof of loss without jeopardizing their loss recovery.

C is correct (Module 2 – Obj 5).
 

Many insurers waive the right for a proof of loss except on exceptional claims, total losses, questionable losses, or losses over a certain monetary amount.

 

A is incorrect. If the proof of loss is rejected, it must be for specific reasons.
B is incorrect. When the insurer receives the proof of loss, it must make a decision within a designated period of time.
D is incorrect. If an insurer requests a proof of loss, the insured has a duty to provide one.

47. The contract of carriage between the carrier and the shipper is referred to as the:
A. Master contract.
B. Bill of receipt.
C. Carrier receipt.
D. Bill of lading.

D is correct (Module 9 – Obj 1).
 

The bill of lading is a document acknowledging receipt of goods from the shipper. This document is given by the carrier, and it includes the terms of the contract of carriage for the goods.

48. Determining the replacement cost for merchandise is affected by all of the following, EXCEPT:
A. The cost to insure the merchandise.
B. The cost for opening and tagging merchandise.
C. The cost of incoming freight.
D. Trade discounts and allowances.

A is correct (Module 7 – Obj 2).
 

The replacement cost can be increased by the cost for opening, tagging, marking merchandise, or the cost of freight. The replacement cost can be decreased by trade discounts and allowances. However, the cost to insure the merchandise does not affect the replacement cost.

49. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding Fair Rental Value in Coverage D - Loss of Use?
A. Coverage can be extended to any rental property owned by the insured.
B. Most policies automatically include loss exposures from home-sharing activities.
C. Coverage applies even if the premises was not currently being rented when the loss occurred.
D. Coverage lasts for as long as it takes to find a new occupant.

C is correct (Module 8 – Obj 6).
 

The part of the premises doesn’t have to be rented to a tenant at the time of the loss in order for the insured to be compensated for fair rental value.

 

A is incorrect. Coverage only applies to rentals of the insured’s residence premises.
B is incorrect. Many insurers are modifying their homeowners policies to exclude home-sharing loss exposures.
D is incorrect. Coverage only lasts for the shortest time required to repair or replace the damaged premises.

50. Joe is a 50% owner of a parcel of land that was titled as Joint Tenants With Rights of Survivorship between Joe and his sister. Assuming Joe dies, what will happen to his 50% interest in the property?
A. The interest will pass to his surviving spouse, as declared in Joe’s Will.
B. The interest will pass to his sister for the remainder of her life, then pass to Joe’s surviving spouse.
C. The interest will pass to his sister by operation of law, and she will have full ownership of the property.
D. The interest will be divided up among Joe’s surviving spouse, his children, and his sister.

C is correct (Module 2 – Obj 1).
 

In a joint tenancy, when one tenant dies, the remaining tenants have an automatic right to the deceased tenant’s share.

51. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding coverage for windstorm or hail damage provided under most homeowners policies?
A. Coverage for roof surfacing applies on a replacement cost basis for loss caused by windstorm or hail.
B. The trees, shrubs, and other plants additional coverage does not apply to loss caused by windstorm or hail.
C. Watercraft and their trailers are typically covered for windstorm or hail damage up to $2,500.
D. Deductibles generally do not apply when property is damaged by windstorm or hail.

B is correct (Module 4 – Obj 2).
 

A is incorrect. Coverage for roof surfacing applies on an actual cash value basis.
C is incorrect. Watercraft and their trailers are not covered for windstorm or hail damage, except when the watercraft is located inside a fully enclosed building at the time of the loss (typically covered up to $1,500).
D is incorrect. A deductible typically applies, and the deductible may be a percentage deductible.

52. Which one of the following represents a step that is taken when valuing out-of-sight merchandise?
A. Subtracting the amount that could have been sold from the amount added to inventory between the last physical inventory and the date of the loss.
B. Adding the amount remaining in inventory on the date of the loss to the amount in the last physical inventory.
C. Subtracting the amount that was sold between the last physical inventory and the date of the loss from the amount that could have been sold.
D. Adding the value of the damaged merchandise to the value of the non-damaged merchandise.

C is correct (Module 7 – Obj 3).
 

The following is the formula that can be used to determine the value of out-of-sight inventory:
Amount in last physical inventory
+Amount added to inventory between the last physical inventory and the date of the loss.
=Amount that could have been sold
-Amount that was sold between the last physical inventory and the date of the loss
=Amount remaining in inventory on the date of the loss

53. When goods are being shipped between a buyer and a seller, and the term “FOB (Free on Board) Vessel” is included in the terms of sale, the buyer is responsible for any loss that occurs:
A. When the goods are placed alongside the vessel at the port named in the terms.
B. When the goods are accepted by the carrier for transit.
C. When the goods are placed on the vessel at the port named in the terms.
D. When the goods are delivered to the buyer’s premises.

C is correct (Module 9 – Obj 1).
 

When FOB (Free on Board) Vessel is used, the buyer assumes responsibility for loss as soon as the goods are placed aboard the vessel at the port named in the terms.

 

A is incorrect. Under FAS (Free Along Side) Vessel, the risk of loss passes to the buyer when the goods are placed alongside the vessel at the port named in the terms.
B is incorrect. Under FOB (Free on Board) Point of Origin, the risk of loss passes to the buyer when the goods are accepted by the carrier for transit.
D is incorrect. Under FOB (Free on Board) Destination, the risk of loss passes to the buyer when the goods are delivered to the buyer’s premises.

54. All of the following are questions that can be answered by declaratory judgement action, EXCEPT:
A. What are the limits of liability?
B. Did the loss occur during the policy period?
C. Do other insurance policies apply?
D. What are the amount of damages?correct

D is correct (Module 3 – Obj 4).
 

Declaratory judgement actions are used to help determine whether policy coverage applies to a claim. They do not address the issues of fault or monetary damages.

55. A staged or fictitious loss undertaken by an insured deliberately is referred to as:
A. Hard fraud.
B. Concealment.
C. Soft fraud.
D. Opportunity fraud.

A is correct (Module 5 – Obj 1).
 

B is incorrect. Concealment is an intentional failure to disclose a material fact.
C is incorrect. Soft fraud, also known as opportunity fraud, is fraud that occurs when a legitimate claim is exaggerated.
D is incorrect. Opportunity fraud, also known as soft fraud, is fraud that occurs when a legitimate claim is exaggerated.

56. When merchandise is damaged but still able to be sold, to whom is the merchandise most valuable?
A. A third party seller.
B. The insurer.
C. The salvor.
D. The insured.

D is correct (Module 7 – Obj 1).
 

Merchandise that is damaged but still able to be sold at the retail level is almost certainly worth more to the insured than to anyone else.

57. Which one of the following statements is correct regarding public adjusters?
A. They are not required to be licensed in most states.
B. They are most often involved in analyzing and presenting theft claims.
C. They are hired by the insurer to represent the insurer in claims disputes.
D. They should work with the goal of achieving proper adjustment of a claim.

D is correct (Module 1 – Obj 2).
 

A is incorrect. Most states require public adjusters to be licensed.
B is incorrect. Public adjusters are most often involved in presenting fire claims to insurers.
C is incorrect. Public adjusters are hired by the insured to represent the insured in a claim.

58. Which one of the following represents a way in which proceeds from a salvage sale can be accounted for?
A. Sale on account of whom it may concern.
B. Sale in which salvor coinsures.
C. Sale on account of agent.
D. Sale in which insured subrogates.

A is correct (Module 7 – Obj 4).
 

The four methods of accounting for proceeds from a salvage sale are:

Sale on account of insurer.
Sale on account of insured.
Sale on account of whom it may concern.
Sale in which insured coinsures.


59. The difference between a business’s revenue and its cost of goods sold is its:
A. Operating expenses.
B. Net income.
C. Gross profit.
D. Net worth.

C is correct (Module 8 – Obj 2).
 

Gross profit is an amount reported on the income statement. It is calculated by subtracting cost of goods sold from revenue.

 

A is incorrect. Operating expenses are amounts that are subtracted from gross profit in arriving at net income.
B is incorrect. Net income is gross profit minus operating expenses.
D is incorrect. Net worth represents assets minus liabilities.

60. Which one of the following is considered a direct physical loss at a factory?
A. Loss of income following a flood in the factory.
B. Loss of production time due to an electrical outage.
C. Loss of merchandise due to a fire in a storage room.
D. Overtime labor costs incurred following a tornado.

C is correct (Module 2 – Obj 1).
 

A is incorrect. Loss of income is a financial consequence and not a direct physical loss.
B is incorrect. Loss of production time is a financial consequence and not a direct physical loss.
D is incorrect. Overtime labor costs is a financial consequence and not a direct physical loss.

61. A restoration specialist is responsible for:
A. Separating damaged merchandise from undamaged merchandise.
B. Cleaning equipment, stock, and merchandise following a loss.
C. Determining where and how a fire began.
D. Valuing property.

B is correct (Module 1 – Obj 4).
 

A is incorrect. Salvors separate damaged merchandise from undamaged merchandise. In addition, they establish values of damaged or destroyed business property.
C is incorrect. Origin and cause experts determine where and how a fire began.
D is incorrect. Appraisers have specialized knowledge of the value of property.

62. When a Builders Risk policy is written on a reporting basis, which one of the following is the most important for a claims representative to verify?
A. That there was an insurable interest on the date of the policy inception.
B. If soft costs were incurred.
C. If an equipment floater endorsement was added.
D. That the values reported are accurate.

D is correct (Module 9 – Obj 5).
 

Substantial penalties may result from late or inaccurate reporting. Therefore, a claims rep needs to verify the values reported are accurate.

63. In order for an insurer to void an insurance policy on the basis of concealment, the insurer must prove that the concealment was:
A. False and fraudulent.
B. Misrepresentative and inadvertent.
C. Material and willful.
D. Made in bad faith and false.

C is correct (Module 5 – Obj 2).
 

In order for an insurer to void an insurance policy on the basis of concealment, the insurer must prove that the concealment was material and willful.

64. Under the water damage table from “Mold Prevention in Mold Remediation in Schools and Commercial Buildings,” which one of the following should potentially be frozen in a frost-free freezer in order to prevent mold growth within 24-48 hours after suffering clean water damage?
A. Wood surfaces.
B. Ceiling tiles.
C. Vinyl flooring.
D. Books and papers.

D is correct (Module 4 – Obj 3).
 

A is incorrect. Wood surfaces should be dried using dehumidifiers or fans, or even cleaned with mild detergent.
B is incorrect. Ceiling tiles should be discarded and replaced.
C is incorrect. Vinyl flooring should be vacuumed or damp wiped with water and detergent.

65. Which one of the following represents the proper way for an insurer to demand an examination under oath?
A. In a letter asking the examinee to call the insurer and schedule a time that is mutually convenient.
B. Via a calendar invite sent to the claimant’s business calendar.
C. Through a phone call between the claims representative and the examinee.
D. In a written letter stating the exact date, time, and place for the examination.

D is correct (Module 2 – Obj 6).
 

To be legally binding, a demand letter must be a written notice that includes a definite date, time, and place for the examination.

66. Sandra’s Furniture reflected the following on their books and records:
Revenues - $500,000
Beginning inventory - $350,000.
Inventory purchased during the year - $200,000
Ending inventory - $140,000
The cost of goods sold is:

A. $140,000.
B. $290,000.
C. $320,000.
D. $410,000.

D is correct (Module 7 – Obj 3).
 

The cost of goods sold is calculated as follows:
Beginning inventory - $350,000
Plus: amount added to the inventory - $200,000
Equals: amount that could have been sold - $550,000
Less: ending inventory - ($140,000)
Equals: cost of goods sold - $410,000

67. Kyle and Tom have a building they insure under two separate insurance policies. Policy A has a limit of $200,000 and Policy B has a limit of $400,000. If the insurers use the proportional share method and a covered loss worth $120,000 occurs, Policy B will pay:
A. $0.
B. $60,000.
C. $80,000.
D. $120,000.

C is correct (Module 6 – Obj 5).
 

With the proportional share method, the insurers contribute to the loss payment in the proportion to which they contribute to the total amount of coverage purchased.

 

Policy B’s proportional share = (Policy’s B amount of coverage/Total amount of coverage) x loss
Policy B’s proportional share = ($400,000/($200,000 + $400,000)) x $120,000
Policy B’s proportional share = ($400,000/$600,000) x $120,000
Policy B’s proportional share = 0.6667 x $120,000
Policy B’s proportional share = $80,000

68. Jane owns a gift shop, and her new property insurance policy went into effect on July 1. She files a fire claim on February 16 of the following year for a fire that occurred on February 15. The claim includes losses related to Valentine’s Day cards and decorations. The insurer investigates the claim on February 18. Jane submits receipts and invoices in person to the insurer on February 20, and then calls the adjuster to inquire about payment of the claim on February 22. All of the following are indicators of potential fraud in this case, EXCEPT:
A. The loss occurred in the middle of the policy term.
B. The Valentine’s Day cards were destroyed one day after Valentine’s Day.
C. The insured was pushy for a quick settlement.
D. The insured avoided conducting business by mail.

A is correct (Module 5 – Obj 1).
 

An indicator of fraud would be the loss occurring just after coverage takes effect, just before it ceases, or just after it has been increased.

69. ABC Suit Company had the following transactions with respect to their suit inventory:
Beginning inventory – 200 suits purchased for $200 each
Purchases of suits in February – 100 suits purchased for $300 each
Purchases of suits in March – 200 suits purchased for $250 each
Sales of suits in April – 250 suits
Assuming they sold the oldest suits first, what is the current value of their inventory?

A. $40,000.
B. $55,000.
C. $65,000.
D. $80,000.

C is correct (Module 7 – Obj 3).
 

ABC Suit Company purchased a total of 500 suits (200 + 100 + 200) and they sold 250 suits. The 250 suits sold were the first 250 purchased (oldest suits were sold first).

 

Therefore, the remaining inventory consists of the following:
50 (remaining) suits x $300 = $15,000
200 suits x $250 = $50,000

 

Total value = $65,000

70. John and Susan, a married couple, have a home with a $300,000 replacement cost. They purchased an HO-3 – Special Form policy with a Coverage A – Dwelling limit of $300,000 and a 2% deductible. A strong windstorm causes $15,000 of damage to the home. How much will the insurer pay with respect to this loss?
A. $0.
B. $6,000.
C. $9,000.
D. $15,000.

C is correct (Module 6 – Obj 4).
 

Windstorm is a covered cause of loss under an HO-3 policy. Since John and Susan have satisfied the 80% coinsurance provision, the loss will be reimbursed in full, after subtracting out the deductible.

 

Deductible = $300,000 x 2% = $6,000
Reimbursed loss = $15,000 - $6,000 = $9,000

71. Bob’s Bakery experiences a loss and must partially shut down its operation for a few weeks. Their normal net income for that period would have been $7,000, but during the shutdown the actual net income was $3,000. In addition, they incurred $2,000 of extra expenses. What is the settlement under their Business Income (and Extra Expense) policy?
A. $4,000.
B. $6,000.
C. $8,000.
D. $12,000.

B is correct (Module 8 – Obj 4).
 

The Business Income (and Extra Expense) Coverage Form will cover the loss of net income, plus any Extra Expenses incurred.

 

Projected net income - actual net income = $4,000 loss of net income.
Covered amount = $4,000 lost income + $2,000 extra expenses = $6,000

72. ABC Insurance Company has concluded an investigation of a house fire and has decided to deny the claim due to arson. To avoid defaming the insured, ABC Insurance Company should issue the denial through:
A. An email to agent.
B. A phone call to the insured.
C. A letter to the insured marked “personal and confidential.”correct
D. A general denial letter that makes no mention of arson.

C is correct (Module 3 – Obj 3).
 

For claims denied on the basis of arson, insurers should mark “personal and confidential” on the outside of the denial letter’s envelope to avoid an insured claiming defamation.

73. Merchandise from Ferdinand’s clothing store is damaged. The agreed upon value of the merchandise is $100,000. The claims representative hires a salvor to sell the damaged goods, and the salvor is able to sell the clothing for $45,000. Assuming the salvor charges fee of $2,000, what is the net cost to the insurer for the claim?
A. $47,000.
B. $53,000.
C. $55,000.
D. $57,000.

D is correct (Module 7 – Obj 4).
 

Depending on the method for accounting the salvage proceeds, the insurer will either pay the net proceeds from the salvage sale ($45,000) to the insured or keep the proceeds for its own account. Thus, the net cost to the insurer is:

 

Net cost to insurer = Agreed upon value - proceeds from salvage sale + salvor’s fees
Net cost to insurer = $100,000 - $45,000 + $2,000
Net cost to insurer = $57,000

74. A clause in an ISO Commercial Property Conditions reads:
“If any person or organization to or for whom we make payments under this Coverage Part has rights to recover damages from another, those rights are transferred to us to the extent of our payment. That person or organization must do everything necessary to secure our rights and must do nothing after loss to impair them.”

These rights are granted to the insurer under the policy’s:

A. Reinsurance clause.
B. Declaratory judgment action.
C. Subrogation clause.
D. Reclamation provision.

C is correct (Module 1 – Obj 5).
 

Subrogation is the process by an insurer can, after it has paid a loss under the policy, recover the amount paid from any party (other than the insured) who caused the loss or is otherwise legally liable for the loss.

 

A is incorrect. Reinsurance is the practice whereby insurers transfer portions of their risk to other insurers by some form of agreement to reduce the likelihood of paying a large obligation resulting from an insurance claim.
B is incorrect. Declaratory judgement actions are used to help determine whether policy coverage applies to a claim.
D is incorrect. Commercial insurance policies do not contain a reclamation provision.

75. Gertrude submits a claim for loss due to a windstorm. Strong winds blew rain through an open window, and the drapes and carpet in her living room are severely stained. Allen, the claims representative, determines that the property needs to be replaced and tells Gertrude to replace the property and send him a copy of the invoices. Gertrude complies with Allen’s request. Later, Allen, reviews the policy and discovers that the property is not covered. Allen should:
A. Immediately ask Gertrude to sign a nonwaiver agreement.
B. Cancel the policy.
C. Deny the claim before the invoices are due.
D. Pay the invoices because he waived the right not to.

D is correct (Module 3 – Obj 2).
 

When Allen instructed Gertrude to replace the damaged property and send him the invoices, he waived his right to deny the claim.

76. Walter has submitted a claim and proof of loss to We Insure U Insurance (WIUI). WIUI is investigating the claim, but suspects Walter has committed fraud. WIUI demanded that Walter appear for an examination under oath, but Walter failed to appear at the scheduled time. WIUI should:
A. Send a letter requesting that Walter reschedule.
B. Cancel Walter’s policy.
C. Deny Walter’s claim.
D. Set aside a reserve equal to the expected loss under the policy.

A is correct (Module 2 – Obj 6).
 

If an examinee does not appear at the examination under oath’s appointed date and time, the insurer has three options. One of the options is to send a letter requesting the examinee contact the claims representative to reschedule the examination.

77. Stikrs, D-cals, & Pyns is an online merchant that specializes in producing stickers, decals, and pins based on trending social media memes. It also has a few brick-and-mortar stores in New York and Los Angeles. Which one of the following would be the best way for the merchant to insure the volatile quantity of its stock?
A. Business Income (and Extra Expense) Coverage Form.
B. Value Reporting Form.
C. Annual Transit Insurance.
D. Peak Season Endorsement.

B is correct (Module 7 – Obj 5).
 

The Value Reporting Form allows the insured to report values to the insurer at periodic intervals. The insurer will pay the full amount of any loss that occurs (subject to the policy limit), even if the values on hand at the time of the loss are greater than those last reported to the insurer.

78. Paula’s Pet Hotel had a fire in its building and needed to rent another building to house the animals while repairs were being performed. The cost to rent the other building is a(n):
A. Continuing expense.
B. Noncontinuing expense.
C. Operating expense.
D. Extra expense.

D is correct (Module 8 – Obj 5).
 

Extra expenses are necessary expenses incurred during the period of restoration that would not have been incurred if there had been no direct physical loss.

 

A is incorrect. Continuing expenses are normal expenses of the business that will still be paid during a shutdown. Continuing expenses could include expenses such as payroll.
B is incorrect. Noncontinuing expenses are normal expenses of the business that will stop during a shutdown. Noncontinuing expenses could include expenses such as advertising.
C is incorrect. Operating expenses are normal expenses of the business, such as advertising and utilities.

79. A manufacturing company ships its cargo with a trucking company that is insured under a Motor Truck Cargo (MTC) Liability policy. In which one of the following circumstances would the policy provide coverage?
A. A tornado destroys both the truck and the cargo.
B. A public authority seizes all the cargo on the truck due to suspicion of drug trafficking.
C. The cargo is damaged because it was not packaged properly by the manufacturer.
D. The cargo is destroyed when the truck gets into a traffic accident.

D is correct (Module 9 – Obj 3).
 

MTC liability policies apply only to cargo damage for which the motor carrier is legally liable.

80. The Johnson family has an HO-3 policy with a $500 deductible and a $1,500 special limit on jewelry. A diamond necklace with an actual cash value of $1,800 was stolen from their home. Assuming the insurer chooses to “absorb” the deductible under the policy, how much of the loss will be paid by the insurer?
A. $1,200.
B. $1,300.
C. $1,500.
D. $1,800.

B is correct (Module 6 – Obj 4).
 

The Johnsons have an uninsured loss of $300 ($1,800 loss less the $1,500 special limit) on the diamond necklace. The $300 uninsured loss allows $300 of the deductible to be absorbed because it is the insured’s share of the loss. The remaining $200 of the deductible is subtracted from the $1,500 covered loss, resulting in an insurance recovery of $1,300 ($1,500 - $200).

81. Horace, a claims adjuster, is assigned a theft claim. Which one of the following should be included in his preliminary report provided to the insurer?
A. Suggested reserves on certain coverages.
B. Attorney recommendations.
C. Advance claims handling asset allocation.
D. Summary of the claim’s progress.

A is correct (Module 1 – Obj 1).
 

Preliminary reports have several functions. They can be used to suggest reserves on certain coverages.

82. Miguel is claims rep assigned to a case involving Additional Living Expenses and Fair Rental Value. Which one of the following methods should he use to determine the Fair Rental Value?
A. Add together the amount of extra and necessary expenses the homeowner incurs during the period of restoration.
B. Determine the amount for Additional Living Expenses and add 25%.
C. Use online rental calculators and rental listings to determine a fair price.
D. Ask the homeowner to provide the most recent property tax bill relating to the residence.

C is correct (Module 8 – Obj 6).
 

Claims reps can use rental websites and online calculators to estimate the fair rental value of properties.

83. Stacy books a cruise on Platinum Diamond Cruise Line and brings most of her expensive dresses and jewelry. What type of insurable interest does Platinum Diamond Cruise Line have in this situation?
A. Ownership interest.
B. Exposure to legal liability.
C. Multiple interests.
D. Contractual obligations.

B is correct (Module 2 – Obj 3).
 

Platinum Diamond Cruise Line’s insurable interest is based on potential legal liability for damage to the Stacy’s.

84. An insured suffers a loss of personal property due to water damage inside their house. The insured requests an emergency advance payment to buy clothing and some other household items. In this situation, the claims representative should:
A. Deny the request.
B. Issue the payment after obtaining an advance payment receipt.
C. Request an expense draft to cover the insured’s expenses.
D. Issue the payment and explain to the insured that this will constitute full satisfaction of the claim.

B is correct (Module 3 – Obj 2).
 

An advance payment receipt works in the same way a nonwaiver agreement does and will allow the claims representative to issue an emergency payment to the insured without waiving the insurer’s right to deny the claim.

85. MegaCorp had net income of $800,000 for 20x1, earned equally throughout the year. In 20x2, MegaCorp experienced a total shutdown of their operations for three months. During that time, they had continuing expenses of $300,000, including $50,000 of payroll expenses. How much will be paid by MegaCorp’s Business Income (and Extra Expense) policy?
A. $450,000.
B. $500,000.
C. $750,000.
D. $1,100,000.

B is correct (Module 8 – Obj 4).
 

The missing net income is equal to ¼ the net income from the previous year (3 months/12 months).

Missing net income = $800,000/4 = $200,000 

The coverage form will also pay for the continuing expenses incurred, including payroll.
Net income + continuing expenses = total covered
$200,000 + $300,000 = $500,000